A Guide to the Papers of John Armstrong Chaloner, 1884-1922
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Armstrong Chaloner 1884-1922
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-394-c
75 items (2 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from Jerry N. Showalter on January 14, 1974.
Biographical/Historical Information
A brief biography of Chaloner and his Albemarle County estate "Merry Mill" may be found in Volume 73, January 1965, of The Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, pp. 3-21. The article's chronological history of Chaloner's many lawsuits and explanation of his "X-Faculty" which enabled him to write will no doubt be of help to any researcher. Chaloner's literary writing was all done through his "X-Faculty" which took over his mind. All of his manuscripts are written in blue colored pencil and annotated in red. Chaloner eventually changed his last name to "Chanler," which accounts for both spellings appearing attached to various documents.
Scope and Content
Papers of Chaloner's efforts to reverse the lunacy verdict of the New York Courts, including; correspondence with New York lawyer Hiram Reswell Steele [1842], portions of Chaloner's testimony, his notes re the case and his "betrayal" by Stanford White, petitions for impeachment of the judge who committed him and for safe conduct to present an appeal to the U.S. President.
The collection also contains a letterbook of his secretary, Ernle G. Money, and manuscripts of his poetry and drama including Robbery Under Law, his play about his murder of John Gillard.
Contents List
- Chanler Democratic Club n.d., 7 p. (Box 1)
- New York Supreme Court Summons 1884 Jan. (Box 1)
- Notes on Insanity Case 1916 Aug. 12, AMs/TMs, 5 p. (Box 1)
- Papers on Insanity Case 1912-1913, TMS/autograph notes, 64 p. (Box 1)
- Petition for Impeachment of George C. Holt n.d., printed with autograph notes (Box 1)
- U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals - John Armstrong Chaloner vs. Thomas T. Sherman, petition and opinion 1914-1915 (Box 1)
- The "Buffalo Commercial" 1913 May 4, AMs/TMs (Box 1)
- "The Hazard of the Die" n.d., TMs/autograph notes (Box 1)
- "Maeterlinck" or "John O'Dreams," note to "Scorpio" Sonnet 19 1914 Oct., AMs/TMs (Box 1)
- "Pieces of Eight," a sequence of war sonnets 1914 Sept., TMS/autograph notes (Box 1)
- "Robbery Under the Law" & insertion 1914 Oct. 14, AMs/TMs (Box 1)
- Mss. R.U.P. 1913 April 10, AMs (Box 1)
- "Saul and David" 1915 Dec., 2 pamphlets, 1 with autograph (Box 1)
- "The Serpent of Old Nile" 1915 June-July, AMs/TMs/autograph notes (Box 1)
- Sonnets 1913-1915, AMs/TMs, 14 p. (Box 1)
- "Tale of Orrebel" 1913 Oct. 30, fragments, AMs (Box 2)
- Voltaires Criticism Enlarged 1908 April 30, AMs (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1906-1913, ca. 8 items (Box 2)
- Letterbook chiefly with Ernle G. Money 1920 Oct. 19 (last entry 1922 Sept. 20), ca. 106 p. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Items 1913-1916, 6 p. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Items n.d., ca. 9 p. (Box 2)